and send them to the telescope operator, and then anxiously wait for the data to come back, praying to the weather gods. Now I bet most of you don't have careers that critically depend on whether or not it's cloudy last night. Well, we weren't going to get any second chances here. Because the weather was great, 'Oumuamua decided not to be. Its brightness wasn't constant. Now here we see 'Oumuamua racing between the stars. It's centered in the middle. The stars are trailed out because the telescope is following its motion. It started faint and then it got brighter, fainter, brighter, and fainter again, as sunlight is reflected off of four sides of an oblong object. The extreme brightness change led us to an unbelievable conclusion about its shape. As shown in this artist's impression, 'Oumuamua is apparently very long and narrow, with an axis ratio of about 10 to one. Assuming it's dark, this means it's about half a mile long. Nothing else in our solar system looks like this. We only have a handful of objects that even have an axis ratio bigger than five to one. So we don't know how this forms, but it may be part of its birth process in its home solar system. 'Oumuamua was varying in brightness every 7.34 hours, or so we thought. As more data started to come in from other teams, they were reporting different numbers. Why is it the more we learn about something, the harder it gets to interpret? Well, it turns out that 'Oumuamua is not rotating in a simple way. It's wobbling like a top. So while it is rotating around its short axis, it's also rolling around the long axis and nodding up and down. This very energetic, excited motion is almost certainly the result of it being violently tossed out of its home solar system. Now how we interpret the shape from its brightness depends very critically on how it's spinning, so now we have to rethink what it may look like, and as shown in this beautiful painting by space artist Bill Hartmann, we think that 'Oumuamua may be more of a flattened oval. So let's get back to the energetics. What is it made of? Well, ideally we would love to have a piece of 'Oumuamua into the laboratory, so we could study it in detail. But since even private industry can't manage to launch a spacecraft within a week to something like this, astronomers have to rely on remote observations. So astronomers will look at how the light interacts with the surface. Some colors may get absorbed, giving it a chemical fingerprint, whereas other colors may not. On the other hand, some substances may just reflect more blue or red light efficiently. In the case of 'Oumuamua, it reflected more red light, making it look very much like the organic rich surface of the comet recently visited by the Rosetta spacecraft. But not everything that looks reddish has the same composition. In fact, minerals that have tiny little bits of iron in the surface can also look red, as does the dark side of Saturn's moon Iapetus, shown in these images from the Cassini spacecraft. Nickel-iron meteorites, in other words, metal, can also look red. So while we don't know what's on the surface, we know even less about what's on the inside. However, we do know that it must at least be strong enough to not fly apart as it rotates, so it probably has a density similar to that of rocky asteroids; perhaps even denser, like metal. Well, at the very least, I want to show you one of the beautiful color images that we got from one of the ground-based telescopes. All right, I admit, it's not all that spectacular. (Laughter) We just don't have the resolution. Even Hubble Space Telescope doesn't present a much better view. But the importance of the Hubble data was not because of the images, but because it extended our observations out to two and a half months from the discovery, meaning we get more positions along the orbit, which will hopefully let us figure out where 'Oumuamua came from. So what exactly is 'Oumuamua? We firmly believe it's likely to be a leftover archaeological remnant from the process of the birth of another planetary system, some celestial driftwood. Some scientists think that maybe 'Oumuamua formed very close to a star that was much denser than our own, and the star's tidal forces shredded planetary material early in the solar system's history. Still others suggest that maybe this is something that formed during the death throes of a star, perhaps during a supernova explosion, as planetary material got shredded. Whatever it is, we believe it's a natural object, but we can't actually prove that it's not something artificial. The color, the strange shape, the tumbling motion could all have other explanations. Now while we don't believe this is alien technology, why not do the obvious experiment and search for a radio signal? That's exactly what the Breakthrough Listen project did, but so far, 'Oumuamua has remained completely quiet. Now could we send a spacecraft to 'Oumuamua and answer this question once and for all? Yes, we do actually have the technology, but it would be a long and expensive voyage, and we would get there so far from the Sun that the final approach trajectory would be very difficult. So I think 'Oumuamua probably has many more things to teach us, and in fact there might be more surprises in store as scientists such as myself continue to work with the data. More importantly, I think this visitor from afar has really brought home the point that our solar system isn't isolated. We're part of a much larger environment, and in fact, we may even be surrounded by interstellar visitors and not even know it. This unexpected gift has perhaps raised more questions than its provided answers, but we were the first to say hello to a visitor from another solar system. Thank you. (Applause) Jedidah Isler: Thanks, Karen. I of course enjoyed that talk very much. Thank you. As I recall, we found it pretty late in its journey towards us. Will future technologies like the Large Synoptic Survey Telescope help us detect these things sooner? Karen Meech: Yeah. We're hoping that we'll start to see a lot of these things, and ideally, you'd love to find one as it's approaching the Sun, because you want to have time to do all the science, or even more ideal, you'd get a spacecraft ready to go, parked somewhere in the L4 or L5 position, somewhere near Earth, so that when something comes by, you can chase it. JI: Awesome, thanks so much. Let's thank Karen again. (Applause)
enviarlas al operador del telescopio y luego esperar ansiosamente que nos lleguen los datos, mientras rezamos a los dioses del clima. Apuesto a que la mayoría de Uds. no tienen profesiones que dependan estrechamente de una noche nublada o despejada. Aquí no tendríamos una segunda oportunidad. El tiempo estuvo a nuestro favor, pero 'Oumuamua decidió no estarlo. Su luminosidad no era constante. Aquí vemos a 'Oumuamua desplazándose entre las estrellas. Está ubicado en el medio. Las estrellas dejan un trazo porque el telescopio sigue su movimiento. Se desvanecía y se iluminaba de forma intermitente, como cuando la luz solar se refleja en los cuatro lados de un objeto oblongo. Los notables cambios en su luminosidad nos llevaron a una conclusión increíble sobre su forma. Tal como se muestra en esta impresión artística, 'Oumuamua es aparentemente muy largo y estrecho, con una relación axial aproximada de 10 a 1. Asumiendo que es oscuro, significa que tiene unos 800 m de longitud. No hay nada en nuestro sistema solar que se le asemeje. Incluso son muy pocos los objetos con una relación axial mayor de 5 a 1. No sabemos cómo se formó, pero pudo ser parte del proceso de origen de su propio sistema solar. 'Oumuamua variaba su luminosidad cada 7,34 horas, o al menos eso creíamos. A medida que recibíamos más datos de diferentes equipos, obteníamos números diferentes. ¿Por qué será que mientras más conocemos algo, más difícil se nos hace interpretarlo? Pues bien, resulta que 'Oumuamua no rota de una manera simple. Se tambalea como una tapa. Así que mientras rota sobre su eje más corto, también rota sobre su eje más largo y se balancea de un lado a otro. Este movimiento tan energético y dinámico es casi seguro el resultado de haber sido expulsado violentamente de su sistema solar. Interpretar su forma a partir de su luminosidad depende fundamentalmente de la forma en que rota, así que debemos replantearnos su apariencia, y tal como se ve en esta bella pintura del artista espacial Bill Hartmann, pensamos que 'Oumuamua puede ser más como un óvalo plano. Volvamos a la energética. ¿De qué está compuesto? Lo ideal sería tener un fragmento de 'Oumuamua en el laboratorio para poder estudiarlo en detalle. Pero como ni siquiera el sector privado es capaz de lanzar una nave espacial en una semana para estudiar algo así, los astrónomos se tienen que conformar con las observaciones remotas. Así, observan cómo la luz interactúa con la superficie. Algunos colores se absorben y dejan una huella química, mientras que otros colores no lo hacen. Por otro parte, algunas sustancias reflejan más eficientemente la luz azul o roja. En el caso de 'Oumuamua, reflejaba más luz roja, asemejándolo a la superficie rica en componentes orgánicos del cometa que la nave espacial Rosetta visitó hace muy poco. Pero no todo lo que se ve rojizo tiene la misma composición. De hecho, los minerales con minipartículas de hierro en la superficie también pueden verse rojos, como el lado oscuro de la luna de Saturno, Jápeto, que vemos en estas imágenes tomadas desde la nave espacial Cassini. Meteoritos de níquel y hierro, es decir, metal, también pueden verse rojos. Así como ignoramos qué hay en la superficie, menos sabemos qué hay en su interior. Lo que sabemos es que debe ser al menos lo suficientemente fuerte para no despedazarse a medida que rota, así que posiblemente tenga una densidad similar a la de los asteroides rocosos, o quizá sea más denso, como el metal. Bien, al menos quisiera enseñarles una de las hermosas imágenes a color que obtuvimos con uno de los telescopios en tierra. Lo admito, no es tan espectacular. (Risas) No tienen resolución. Ni siquiera el telescopio espacial Hubble nos da una mejor imagen. Pero la importancia de los datos del Hubble no son las imágenes, sino que extendió nuestras observaciones a dos meses y medio después del descubrimiento, es decir que tendremos más posiciones a lo largo de la órbita que quizá nos permitirán descubrir de dónde proviene 'Oumuamua. Ahora bien, ¿qué es 'Oumuamua exactamente? Creemos firmemente que es un remanente arqueológico del proceso de formación de otro sistema planetario, como material cósmico a la deriva. Algunos científicos piensan que quizá 'Oumuamua se formó muy cerca de una estrella mucho más densa que la nuestra, y que las fuerzas de marea de esa estrella despedazaron material planetario en los comienzos del sistema solar. Otros sugieren que quizá se formó durante la agonía de una estrella, quizá durante la explosión de una supernova, causando desprendimiento de material planetario. Sea lo que sea, creemos que es un objeto natural, aunque no podemos probar que no es artificial. El color, la forma extraña, el movimiento bamboleante podrían tener otras explicaciones. Si bien creemos que no es tecnología extraterrestre, ¿por qué no hacemos la típica prueba de buscar señales de radio? Eso fue exactamente lo que hizo el proyecto "Breakthrough Listen" pero, hasta ahora, 'Oumuamua no ha dado ninguna señal. Ahora bien, ¿podríamos enviar una nave espacial hacia 'Oumuamua y así responder a todas las preguntas? Sí, tenemos la tecnología pero sería un viaje largo y costoso, y estaríamos tan lejos del Sol que el trayecto final de acercamiento sería muy difícil. Pienso que 'Oumuamua aún tiene mucho que enseñarnos e incluso podría haber más sorpresas mientras más científicos seguimos trabajando con los datos. Lo más importante es que este visitante lejano nos demostró que nuestro sistema solar no está aislado. Somos parte de un universo mucho más grande e incluso podríamos estar rodeados de visitante interestelares sin saberlo. Este regalo inesperado quizá haya generado más preguntas que respuestas, pero fuimos los primeros en decirle "hola" al primer visitante de otro sistema solar. Gracias. (Aplausos) Jedidah Isler: Gracias, Karen. Disfruté mucho de tu charla. Gracias. Según recuerdo, lo descubrimos ya tarde en su viaje hacia la Tierra. ¿Será posible que tecnologías futuras como el Gran Telescopio para Sondeos puedan detectar estos objetos con más anticipación? Karen Meech: Sí, esperamos ver más objetos como estos e, idealmente, nos gustaría descubrirlos en su camino al Sol porque queremos tener tiempo para poder estudiarlos, e incluso mejor sería tener una nave espacial lista para despegar, estacionarla en las posiciones L4 o L5, cerca de la Tierra, de modo que cuando algún objeto se acerque podamos perseguirlo. JL: Fantástico, muchas gracias. Una vez más, gracias a Karen. (Aplausos)